Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts at the Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- To one a century hence, or any number of centuries hence, 1857-1859; uva.00335; xxx.00066; xxx.00109; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 10 x 13 cm pasted to 11.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  On one composite leaf of pink paper formed of two sections (10 x 13 and 11.5 x 13 cm) of the same page cut apart and pasted together in a new order. The poem number was originally 101 and then changed to 102; this number was deleted and the current ?101 added in fine pen. Bowers explains that the poem, in two discrete verse sections and inscribed in black ink (with title), originally occupied one full side of this leaf. When Whitman wanted to expand the first section without having to retranscribe the second one, he simply cut the two sections apart, flipped the first section over (turning it upside-down in the process), pasted the second section to the lower edge of the verso of the first section, and wrote his new first section (beginning "Throwing far, throwing over the head/ of death" and incorporating the original title as verse 3) in the blank space now created above the second section. The new first section is written and revised in light ink. As Bradley and Blodgett observe, the words "thirty-eight years old the/ eighty-first year of The States" indicate that Whitman composed the poem in 1857; these were revised to read "I, forty years old the Eighty-third Year of The States" in the 1860 Leaves, in which this poem constituted section 45 of Calamus. In 1867 Whitman retitled the poem Full of Life, Now.
- Feuillage, 1857-1859; uva.00185; xxx.00114; poetry handwritten 16 leaves 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This poem was originally numbered 89. Whitman also numbered each leaf in the lower-left corner in pencil: the leaves follow the order 1-9, 9 1/2 (a full page despite its number), and 10-15. The expression "the Eightieth year of / These States" at the top of leaf 2 indicates that Whitman was working on this poem as early as 1856. It became section 4 of Chants Democratic in 1860. In 1867 Whitman ungrouped it and retitled the poem American Feuillage, a name it kept until being permanently retitled Our Old Feuillage in 1881.
- Evolutions, 1857-1859; uva.00187; xxx.00129; poetry handwritten 6 leaves 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  On six leaves of pink paper. The deleted title is Poemet—. Evolutions.— is written in light ink, and the number "41—" in a darker ink than the text. Whitman numbered each leaf in pencil in the upper right corner. This poem was first published in the January 14, 1860 issue of the New York Saturday Press under the title You and Me and To-day, after which it became section 7 of Chants Democratic in the 1860 Leaves of Grass. In 1867 Whitman ungrouped it and permanently retitled it With Antecedents; in 1881 it was permanently transferred to the new cluster Birds of Passage. The manuscript leaves correspond to the published verses in the 1860 Leaves of Grass.
- A Sunset Carol, 1857-1859; uva.00188; xxx.00297; poetry handwritten 6 leaves leaf 1 25.5 x 12.5 cm, leaves 2-6 21.5 x 12.5 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Whitman numbered each of the six leaves, in pencil, in the upper right corner. In the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass Whitman published this poem as section 8 of Chants Democratic. In 1867, he gave it the permanent title Song at Sunset and moved it to the supplement Songs Before Parting; in 1871 it was finally transferred to the cluster Songs of Parting within the main body of Leaves of Grass.
- Thought [Of these years I sing], 1857-1859; uva.00189; xxx.00309; xxx.00413; poetry handwritten 2 leaves leaf 1 21.5 x 13 cm, leaf 2 18.5 x 12.5 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Whitman inscribed and circled the note "2d/ piece/ in Book" in the upper-right corner of the first leaf. The small top section is inscribed on the verso of some deleted draft verses excised from So Long! Thought became section 9 of Chants Democratic in 1860. In the 1867 Leaves of Grass Whitman combined it with the second Thought to form the poem Thoughts in the supplement Songs Before Parting. (This particular Thought was numbered section 1 of the composite poem.) In 1871 Thoughts appeared in the cluster Songs of Parting within the main body of Leaves of Grass, and in 1881, it achieved its final position within that cluster. These leaves correspond to the verses in the 1860 Chants Democratic version.
- Thought [Of closing up my songs by these], 1857-1859; uva.00190; xxx.00413; xxx.00047; poetry handwritten 2 leaves leaf 1 9 x 12.5 cm pasted to 17.5 x 13.5 cm, leaf 2 21 x 13.5 cm (Folder 50-51)
  The paste-on revision contains an expanded version of the original lines Whitman cut away and apparently discarded. The verso of the paste-on section contains, five undeleted draft lines that would become the final verses of Proto-Leaf in the 1860 Leaves of Grass; Whitman's small note in the lower-right corner, in a semi-circle, reads "end of Poem." These Thought lines became section 11 of Chants Democratic in 1860. In the 1867 Leaves of Grass Whitman combined it with the second Thought to form the poem Thoughts in the supplement Songs Before Parting. In 1871 Thoughts appeared in the cluster Songs of Parting within the main body of Leaves of Grass, and in 1881, it achieved its final position within that cluster.
- To a Historian, 1857-1859; uva.00191; xxx.00028; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 20 x 16 cm pasted to 11 x 16 cm (Folder 50-51)
  After undergoing extensive revisions, in 1860 To a Historian became section 10 of Chants Democratic. In 1867 Whitman deleted five verses, transferred the poem to the supplement Songs Before Parting, and permanently retitled it To a Historian. It appeared as the fifth poem in the opening cluster Inscriptions in the 1872 and all later editions. On the verso appear fragments of pencil notes for a speech or essay Whitman wrote (most likely) in 1856, and revised in 1858, under the working title Slavery—the Slaveholders—/ —The Constitution—the true America and Americans, the laboring persons—. The verso of another manuscript in this collection entitled To a Cantatrice.— contains an additional fragment of these notes.
- Orators, 1857-1859; uva.00193; xxx.00237; poetry handwritten 5 leaves 22 x 13.5 cm (Folder 50-51)
  The poem was originally numbered 67, and the partly erased pencil note "Needs to be/ re-written/ or excluded" appears in the upper-right corner of the first leaf. Whitman also numbered the leaves in pencil in their lower-left corners. The leaves correspond to verses in section 12 of Chants Democratic in the 1860 Leaves of Grass. After excising and altering numerous verses of the poem and numbering different verse paragraphs for the Chants Democratic version, Whitman next made the poem the second numbered section of the last Leaves of Grass cluster in the 1867 edition. From 1872 to 1876 it bore the title To Oratists. Then, in 1881, Whitman deleted several lines, joining this poem with a previously unconnected poem known as Voices to form Vocalism in the cluster Autumn Rivulets, a position and identity the now-composite poem retained from that point on.
- American Laws, 1857-1859; uva.00195; xxx.00240; poetry handwritten 3 leaves leaf 1 19.5 x 12.5 cm, leaves 2-3 21.5 x 12.5 cm (Folder 50-51)
  A partial horizontal line at the top of the first leaf indicates that Whitman cut away the original title and number. Whitman numbered each leaf in pencil in the lower left corner. These pages were transformed into section 13 of Chants Democratic in the 1860 Leaves of Grass. In 1867 it was greatly shortened and transferred to the final Leaves of Grass cluster. In 1872 the poem was permanently retitled Laws for Creations Its final position was in the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
- To Poets to Come, 1857-1859; uva.00196; xxx.00045; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 20 x 16 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Whitman numbered the inscribed sides of the folded leaf, in pencil, in the upper right corners. Side 1 corresponds to verses 1-9 of section 14 of Chants Democratic in the 1860 Leaves of Grass; side 2 ("I expect that Kanadians,") became verses 10-16 of that version. In 1867 it was shortened to make up section 4 of the final Leaves of Grass cluster. In 1872 it was permanently retitled Poets to Come and transferred to the cluster The Answerer, where it stayed until being moved to the Inscriptions cluster in 1881.
- Mediums, 1857-1859; uva.00197; xxx.00281; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21.5 x 12.5 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This manuscript draft became section 16 of Chants Democratic in 1860, with Leaf 1 corresponding to verses 1-6 and Leaf 2 ("They shall train themselves/ to go in public,...") to verses 7-11. In 1867 Whitman restored the title Mediums; in 1871, the poem was transferred to Passage to India, and in 1881 took its final position in the cluster From Noon to Starry Night.
- Wander-Teachers, 1857-1859; uva.00198; xxx.00036; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  The poem was originally numbered 50. Whitman penciled in a question mark, in parentheses, in the upper-right corner. This became section 17 of Chants Democratic in the 1860 Leaves of Grass, with leaf 1 corresponding to verses 1-6 and leaf 2 ("We confer on equal terms with / each of The States,") to verses 7-13. Although he dropped it from Leaves of Grass in 1867, Whitman nonetheless used the poem, permanently retitled On Journeys through the States, in Passage to India in 1871. In 1872 and 1876 it appeared in the Passage to India annexes to Leaves of Grass and Two Rivulets, respectively, and in the 1881 edition it took its final position in the cluster Inscriptions.
- Leaf [Me imperturbe!], 1857-1859; uva.00199; xxx.00038; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 73. This poem became section 18 of Chants Democratic in 1860; in 1867 it was permanently retitled Me Imperturbe, and after various repositionings, was finally transferred to the cluster Inscriptions in 1881.
- Leaf [I was looking a long while], 1857-1859; uva.00200; xxx.00241; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 75; the pencil title Leaflet appears, deleted, in the upper-right corner. This poem became section 19 of Chants Democratic in 1860; in 1867 it was permanently retitled I Was Looking a Long While, and in 1881 was assigned to the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
- Mouth-Songs, 1857-1859; uva.00201; xxx.00041; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 54 and titled Leaf.—. The title was next Songs—always wanted and then Mouth-Songs. This poem became section 20 of Chants Democratic in 1860, with leaf 1 corresponding to verses 1-6 and leaf 2 ("The delicious singing of the/ mother...") to verses 8-10. In 1867 Whitman revised the first line and permanently retitled the poem I Hear America Singing; in 1881 it achieved its final position in the cluster Inscriptions.
- Confession and Warning, 1857-1859; uva.00202; xxx.00239; poetry handwritten 3 leaves 21.5 x 12 cm (Folder 50-51)
  After undergoing substantial deletions and revisions this poem became section 13 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in 1860, with the manuscript leaves corresponding to the published version as follows: leaf 1 to numbered verse paragraphs 1 (now beginning "O bitter sprig! Confession sprig!") through 3 and 5; leaf 2 ("You felons on trial in courts,") to 4 and most of 6; and leaf 3 ("And I say I am of them—") to the rest of 6. In 1867 Whitman permanently retitled the poem You Felons on Trial in Courts and further shortened it by removing the first three verse paragraphs. The poem's final position, in 1881, was in the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
- Night on the Prairies, 1857-1859; uva.00203; xxx.00016; poetry handwritten 3 leaves 20 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Whitman cut off and flipped over the top section of the first leaf, gluing it to the rest of the leaf, in order to transform the original first line into the title. (The current verso of the top section still bears, undeleted, the first line "Night on the prairies[,]" along with the title Leaf.— and the number 73, originally 72). Whitman deleted the pencil numbers 16, 17, and 18 in the lower-left corner of the leaves, substituting the numbers 1 through 3. This poem became section 15 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in 1860. In 1867 Whitman restored the title Night on the Prairies and revised the poem, transferring it to the Leaves of Grass group. After other repositionings it achieved its current place in the cluster Whispers of Heavenly Death in 1881.
- Leaf [Sea-water, and all breathing], 1857-1859; uva.00204; xxx.00137; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 22 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  The poem was originally numbered 71 and then modified to 72. These 2 leaves contain verses first published in section 16 of the 1860 Leaves of Grass cluster. In 1867 Whitman transferred this poem to a different Leaves of Grass group with the poems that would become Night on the Prairies and I Sit and Look Out. After receiving the title The World Below the Brine in the 1871 Sea-Shore Memories group of Passage to India, the final change was its transfer to the cluster Sea Drift within the main body of Leaves of Grass in 1881.
- Leaf [I sit and look out upon all], 1857-1859; uva.00205; xxx.00153; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 77 and then changed to 78. This became section 17 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 Leaves. After taking different positions in both the 1867 and 1872, it took its final place in 1881 in the cluster By the Roadside.
- As of the The Truth, 1857-1859; uva.00206; xxx.00276; poetry handwritten 4 leaves leaf 2 19.5 x 13 cm, all other leaves 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This poem became section 18 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 edition. In 1872 the poem received the title All is Truth, and in 1881, after various repositionings, it was finally transferred to the cluster From Noon to Starry Night. The second leaf is a composite formed when Whitman deleted and cut away the original first two verses on the leaf, flipped the new small section over and upside-down, pasted it to the foot of the remaining original verses, and inscribed a verse in light ink on the newly created blank space.
- As of Origins, 1857-1859; uva.00208; xxx.00147; poetry handwritten 1 leaf three pasted sections of 6.5 x 13 cm, 8 x 13 cm, and 12.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This poem became section 19 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 edition. In 1867 Whitman moved it to a different Leaves of Grass group in the Songs Before Parting annex. In 1872 it was retitled Germs and was ultimately transferred, in 1881, to the cluster By the Roadside.
- Voices, 1857-1859; uva.00209; xxx.00237; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This poem became section 21 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 edition. In 1867 Whitman placed it after what would eventually become All is Truth and Germs as section 3 of a Leaves of Grass group in the annex Songs Before Parting. In 1872 Whitman restored the title Voices. In 1881 he dropped the first two verses and added Voices (as verse paragraph 2) to the previously unrelated poem To Oratists to form Vocalism in the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
- Leaf [What am I after all but a], 1857-1859; uva.00210; xxx.00247; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This poem became section 22 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 edition. In 1867 Whitman dropped the second 1860 verse and made it section 4 of a Leaves of Grass group in the annex Songs Before Parting. Whitman gave it the title What Am I After All in Passage to India (1871), and in 1881 it was finally transferred to the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
- To One Shortly To Die, 1857-1859; uva.00211; xxx.00015; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 95 and then changed to 96. This poem was published under the title To One Shortly to Die, with only minor revisions, in the 1860 Messenger Leaves cluster. In 1871, Whitman made small but significant additions to the poem and transferred it to the supplement Passage to India. In 1881 it was finally moved to the cluster Whispers of Heavenly Death.
- To Rich Givers, 1857-1859; uva.00212; xxx.00154; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  To Rich Givers— was originally numbered 98. In 1860 it formed part of the Messenger Leaves cluster under the same title. After being ungrouped (1867) and transferred to the cluster Songs of Parting (1872 and 1876), it finally appeared, in 1881, in the cluster By the Roadside. The deleted verses on the back of the leaf represent an earlier version of the manuscript poem To the Future, never published by Whitman, and currently housed in the Huntington Library.
- To a Pupil, 1857-1859; uva.00213; xxx.00245; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 12 cm (Folder 50-51)
  The manuscript bears the title To a Pupil; however, the original title seems to have been cut away. This poem was revised somewhat and published under the same title in the Messenger Leaves cluster of the 1860 Leaves of Grass. It was ungrouped in 1867, transferred to a Leaves of Grass group within the Passage to India supplement in 1872 (also 1876), and finally moved to the cluster Autumn Rivulets within Leaves of Grass in 1881.
- A Past Presidentiad, and one to come also, 1857-1859; uva.00214; xxx.00171; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Whitman wrote and deleted the date 1858 in blue pencil in the upper right corner of the first leaf, and inscribed the same date in normal pencil in the lower left corner of the second leaf. This poem became To The States, To Identify the 16th, 17th, or 18th Presidentiad in the cluster Messenger Leaves in the 1860 Leaves of Grass. Ungrouped in 1867, it was transferred in 1872 to a Leaves of Grass group within the main body. In 1881 it was finally transferred to the cluster By the Roadside. Images of the versos are unavailable.
- To a Cantatrice, 1857-1859; uva.00215; xxx.00037; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 9 x 16 cm (Folder 50-51)
  This poem was first titled To an artist, then To an architect; the smudged-out words "Lecture[s] / To" appear in light ink in the upper-left corner. These lines were revised and published under the title To a Cantatrice in the Messenger Leaves cluster of 1860. After being ungrouped and permanently retitled To A Certain Cantatrice in 1867, it was revised for inclusion in the cluster Songs of Insurrection in the 1872 and 1876 Leaves of Grass. In 1881 it was finally transferred to the cluster Inscriptions. On one section of the same leaf of white ruled laid paper used for To a Historian, and with another fragment of the same pencil draft of the speech or essay Slavery—the Slaveholders—/ —The Constitution—the/ true America and Ameri-/ cans, the laboring persons.— on verso.
- To You, 1857-1859; uva.00216; xxx.00412; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 9 x 12.5 pasted to 20 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Beneath the pasted-over section can be discerned a second title, also To You, with the number 91 (mended from 90). In the 1860 Leaves of Grass Whitman divided the poems again, publishing them in reverse order under the same titles at the end of the cluster Messenger Leaves. Section 1 was eventually published (1881) as one of the poems in the cluster Inscriptions, but Whitman dropped section 2 from his published poems after an 1876 appearance in the supplement Passage to India.
- Mannahatta, 1857-1859; uva.00217; xxx.00275; poetry handwritten 5 leaves 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  A draft of the poem Mannahatta. Whitman numbered each leaf in pencil in the lower-left corner. The leaves correspond to various verses in the 1860 edition. In the 1872 edition of Leaves of Grass the poem was transferred to a Leaves of Grass cluster, and in 1881 took its final position in the From Noon to Starry Night cluster.
- Poem of Joys, 1857-1859; uva.00218; xxx.00115; poetry handwritten 20 leaves 14.5 x 13 cm to 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  These twenty leaves, numbered by a collector, relate to Poem of Joys, first published in the 1860 Leaves of Grass. The title became Poems of Joy in 1867, but reverted to the original title in its next two iterations (in the Passage to India supplement of 1872 and 1876). In 1881 it was finally titled A Song of Joys and left independent of any cluster.
- France, the 18th Year of These States, 1857-1859; uva.00221; xxx.00126; poetry handwritten 5 leaves 21 x 13 cm to 22.5 x 13.5 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 86 and revised by overwriting to 87; Whitman also numbered the leaves 1-5 (in pencil, lower left corner), with the 1 replacing a 6 and the 2 written over what looks like a 7. The leaves correspond to various verses in the 1860 published version France, The 18th Year of These States. Although Whitman never changed the title, and did not revise the poem much, he did transfer it twice, grouping it in the cluster Songs of Insurrection within the main body of Leaves of Grass in 1871 and 1876, and in 1881 finally transferring it to the new cluster Birds of Passage within Leaves of Grass.
- Unnamed Lands, 1857-1859; uva.00222; xxx.00231; poetry handwritten 5 leaves 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 81 and revised by overwriting to 82, with the note "?/(Leaf of)" above the number and title. Whitman numbered the leaves 1-5 in pencil in the lower left corners. The leaves correspond to various numbered sections of the 1860 published version. In the 1872 Leaves of Grass Whitman transferred the poem to a Leaves of Grass group, and in 1881 it was finally moved, after several revisions through the different published versions, to the cluster Autumn Rivulets.
- Kosmos, 1857-1859; uva.00224; xxx.00248; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21.5 x 12.5 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 55 and revised by overwriting to 56. Leaf 1 corresponds to verses 1-6 of the 1860 version, and the lines on leaf 2 ("Who out of the theory of the/ earth,...") correspond to verses 7-10. Revised very little through the different editions, Kosmos appeared in 1872 and 1876 in a Leaves of Grass group in the supplement Passage to India. In 1881 it was finally transferred to the cluster Autumn Rivulets within the main body of Leaves of Grass.
- A hand-mirror, 1857-1859; uva.00225; xxx.00145; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally titled Looking-Glass and numbered 82 and revised by overwriting to 83. The poem remained unchanged and with the same title since its first appearance in the 1860 edition. This poem was titled but ungrouped until 1881, when Whitman finally placed it in the cluster By the Roadside.
- Savantism, 1857-1859; uva.00226; xxx.00039; poetry handwritten 1 leaf 21 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  Originally numbered 52 and revised by overwriting to 53. Ungrouped in the 1860 and 1867 Leaves of Grass, the poem Savantism was transferred to Passage to India in 1871 and from there to Leaves of Grass groups in the Passage to India annexes of the 1872 Leaves of Grass and the 1876 Two Rivulets. From there it was moved, finally (in 1881), to the Inscriptions cluster within the main body of Leaves of Grass.
- Says, 1857-1859; uva.00227; xxx.00417; xxx.00419; poetry handwritten 2 leaves 21 x 12.5 cm to 21.5 x 13 cm (Folder 50-51)
  These manuscript lines were revised to form numbered sections 1 through 4 of the ungrouped poem Says in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman cut four verse paragraphs from the poem in the 1867 Leaves of Grass version; from that point on the shortened poem appeared, ungrouped, under the title Suggestions until its final appearance in 1876.